<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on rostrum.blog</title>
    <link>/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on rostrum.blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Motivate yourself with an .Rprofile</title>
      <link>/2019/01/04/rprofile-motivate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/04/rprofile-motivate/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Hang in there, buddy (via Giphy)
 What’s an R profile? It’s a file that contains R code that runs when you start or restart R. You can use it to customise your environment. For example, you could set options, create functions or load packages.
There’s lots of information in the R startup chapter of Colin Gillespie’s’s Efficient R Programming book.
But beware: use of an R profile may not be particularly reproducible if the .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The NBA Northwest Division with gmapsdistance</title>
      <link>/2018/12/24/nba-travel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/24/nba-travel/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Classic Jazz: Stockton to Malone for the dunk (via Giphy)
 TL;DR The gmapsdistance R package lets you query the Google Maps API. I used it to look at travel distances between basketball teams. Surprise: they can be far apart even if they’re in the same division.
 The NBA The USA is pretty big.
So the National Basketball Association (NBA) is separated geographically into Eastern and Western conferences, each with three divisions of five teams.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogdown: change Lithium theme font-face</title>
      <link>/2018/11/29/fontface-lithium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/29/fontface-lithium/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Lithium by Nirvana (via Giphy)
 Blogdown and Hugo themes You can change the default font face for your Blogdown blog by downloading new ones from Google Fonts and adjusting some CSS.
Sections 2.5.1 and 2.7 of the Blogdown book refer to the ability to change fonts for your site. This post explains how to do it for the Lithium theme – the theme being used on this site.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantify colour with magick</title>
      <link>/2018/11/25/art-of-the-possible/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/25/art-of-the-possible/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Walrus with rainbow vomit, of course (via Giphy)
 Colour search Lots of online services let you sort images by colour. Some examples:
 Google Arts &amp;amp; Culture Designspiration TinEye Multicolr  These services must have extracted and quantified each image’s colours. There’s probably a simple way of doing this in R, so let’s give it a go.
By ‘simple’ I mean we’re not going to do any hard work or consider any colour theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waggle dance with ggbeeswarm and emoGG</title>
      <link>/2018/11/21/waggle-dance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/21/waggle-dance/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
A bee scene from irreverent 90s Nicktoon ‘Hey Arnold!’ (via Giphy)
 How to plot grouped continuous data? A boxplot lets you show continuous data split by categories, but it hides the data points and doesn’t tell you much about distribution. A violin chart will show the distribution but you still don’t know about the density of data.
Stripcharts show the data for each category as individual points.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R training featuring Pokemon</title>
      <link>/2018/11/04/r-train-pkmn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/04/r-train-pkmn/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Psyduck hurt itself in its confusion (via Giphy)
 You teach me and I’ll teach you I recently shared some materials that I made to help some colleagues understand and start to use R Markdown as part of a reproducible workflow.
Well, now I’m sharing another thing I made. It’s called Beginner R and RStudio Training (featuring Pokemon!). It’s an introduction to R, RStudio, R Projects, directory structure and the Tidyverse for beginners… and uses Pokemon Go data that I collected myself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R session info info</title>
      <link>/2018/10/13/sessioninfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/13/sessioninfo/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
US Attorney-General Jeff Sessions-Info (via Giphy)
 What’s session info? Session info is just some details about your working environment like your version of R, the locale it’s running from and any loaded packages.
It gives a snapshot to help people reproduce what you’ve done or spot any anomalies. You might get asked for this if someone is diagnosing your R problem. You may also see it at the end of blog posts or reports.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knitting Club: R Markdown for beginners</title>
      <link>/2018/09/24/knitting-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/24/knitting-club/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Knitting simulator by Kara Stone and Gabby DaRienzo (via Giphy)
 RAP and the rise of reproducibility The UK government has got better at producing statistical reports in a reproducible way. A turning point was the creation of Reproducible Analytical Pipelines (RAP) – a method for making releases easier to recreate, test and audit. Matthews Upson and Gregory of Government Digital Service (GDS) have described and enshrined this process and enabled others to continue its spread.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EARL 2018: Crosstalk in memes</title>
      <link>/2018/09/12/crosstalk-memes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/12/crosstalk-memes/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
I refuse to let the doge meme die
 EARL 2018 I gave a talk called Crosstalk: Shiny-like without Shiny1 at the EARL 2018 conference in London.
The crosstalk package by Joe Cheng allows HTML widgets – JavaScript visualisations wrapped in R code – to interact with each other. This can be done inside an R Markdown document (including Flexdashboard) for easy server-less sharing in HTML format.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engifification in R with gifski</title>
      <link>/2018/07/26/engifification-in-r-with-gifski/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/07/26/engifification-in-r-with-gifski/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
A sloth. On a pizza slice. In space. (via Giphy)
 gifski::gifski() You and I both know that the world needs more intergalatic-sloth-pizza gifs.
Great news: ‘the fastest gif encoder in the universe’ has been created. The gifski package for R is now in CRAN. It’s a simple yet fast and powerful way to create gifs from within R, built by Jeroen Oom (@opencpu) for ROpenSci.
The obvious application is for creating gifs from plots, as in the following example from the ROpenSci announcement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Footballers are younger than you</title>
      <link>/2018/07/17/world-cup-age-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/07/17/world-cup-age-app/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
TL;DR I wrote an R Shiny app that tells you how many players at World Cup 2018 were younger than you. It’s designed to make you feel old. You’re welcome.
Here’s some solid reviews I’ve received so far:
 Very depressing
  I knew I was too old to become a great footballer
  Just what I needed to see
 Thanks folks!
 I was at the World Cup Final Extremely rare and valuable tickets for the (CONIFA) World Cup final</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Markov-chaining my PhD thesis</title>
      <link>/2018/06/30/markov-chain-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/30/markov-chain-phd/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Design of the invertebrate feeding experiment
 Doc rot I wrote a PhD thesis in 2014 called Effects of multiple environmental stressors on litter chemical composition and decomposition. See my viva presentation slides here if you don’t really like words.
On graduation day, a stranger came up to me and, to paraphrase, said ‘you doctors should be proud of what you’ve achieved, you’re doing a great service’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mail merge in 2018 with R</title>
      <link>/2018/06/26/mail-merge/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/26/mail-merge/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Super cool 90s guy ready to surf the web (via Giphy)
 Two-thousand and late Clip art! Fax machines! CD-ROMs! Dial-up modems! The World Wide Web! Mail merge!
These exotic terms give me flashbacks to computer class at the turn of the millennium.
The last one–mail merge–was taught as a way to autocomplete template Word letters for made-up customers in an Access database. I no longer need to invoice ‘Mr Sonic The-Hedgehog’ for ordering ‘25 chili dogs’, but the general approach of generating the same template multiple times with different information is still pertinent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tid-ye-text with geniusr</title>
      <link>/2018/06/05/tid-ye-text/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/05/tid-ye-text/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
⚠️ Warning: this post contains offensive words. ⚠️
Genius? Kanye West released his latest album – ye – last week1 after a(nother) pretty turbulent and controversial period of his life2. So what’s been on his mind?
I think the real question is why don’t we scrape Yeezus’s lyrics from the web and analyse them using R? Obviously.
 Genius Genius is a website where you can upload and comment on song lyrics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloudy with a chance of pie</title>
      <link>/2018/05/25/cloud-pie/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/25/cloud-pie/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
The pinnacle of visualisation Great news everyone: I’ve taken the best of two stellar data visualisations and smashed them together into something that can only be described as perfection.
Let me set the scene. There’s three things we can agree on:
Everyone loves pie charts, particularly when they’re in 3D, exploded and tilted. Word clouds aren’t at all overused. I have too much time on my hands.  With that in mind, I’ve artfully melded clouds and pies into the function cloud_pie, which I think sounds rather sweet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pokeballs in Super Smash Bros</title>
      <link>/2018/05/19/pokeballs-in-super-smash-bros/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/19/pokeballs-in-super-smash-bros/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
Smash! Super Smash Bros (SSB) is a beat ’em up videogame series featuring characters from various Nintendo franchises and beyond.
The series has featured on Nintendo 64 (Super Smash Bros, 1998), Gamecube (SSB Melee, 2001), Wii (SSB Brawl, 2008), Wii U and 3DS (SSB ‘4’, 2014) and an upcoming title for the Switch console.
The game is popular enough to have resulted in a series of organised tournaments1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TWO DOGS IN TOILET ELDERLY LADY INVOLVED</title>
      <link>/2018/04/27/two-dogs-in-toilet-elderly-lady-involved/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/27/two-dogs-in-toilet-elderly-lady-involved/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
TL;DR Animals get stuck in weird places. Oh, and the sf package in R can be used for coordinate reprojection prior to interactive mapping with leaflet.
 The problem I often work with data that has coordinates; usually a eastings and northings. I need to convert these to latitude and longitude for interactive mapping using the leaflet package in R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Trek: exploring stardates</title>
      <link>/2018/04/14/r-trek-exploring-stardates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/14/r-trek-exploring-stardates/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
Captain’s log 📖  Star date 71750.51. Our mission is to use R statistical software to extract star dates mentioned in the captain’s log from the scripts of Star Trek: The Next Generation and observe their progression over the course of the show’s seven seasons. There appears to be some mismatch in the frequency of digits after the decimal point – could this indicate poor abillity to choose random numbers?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>