<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on rostrum.blog</title>
    <link>/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on rostrum.blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Mountain Goats with {spotifyr}</title>
      <link>/2019/04/23/mountain-goats/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/23/mountain-goats/</guid>
      <description>Prepare the workspace library(spotifyr) library(dplyr) library(purrr) library(tidyr) You need to sign up for a Spotify developer account and add your client ID and client secret to the environment. This is passed to each of the functions of {spotifyr} to let us access the Spotify API.
access_token &amp;lt;- get_spotify_access_token()  Get albums The get_artist_albums() function takes an artist ID and fetches the albums for that artist.
The Mountain Goats can be identified by the URI spotify:artist:3hyGGjxu73JuzBa757H6R5, where the 22-character value is the artist ID used by {spotifyr}.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The NBA Northwest Division with gmapsdistance</title>
      <link>/2018/12/24/nba-travel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/24/nba-travel/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Classic Jazz: Stockton to Malone for the dunk (via Giphy)
 TL;DR The gmapsdistance R package lets you query the Google Maps API. I used it to look at travel distances between basketball teams. Surprise: they can be far apart even if they’re in the same division.
 The NBA The USA is pretty big.
So the National Basketball Association (NBA) is separated geographically into Eastern and Western conferences, each with three divisions of five teams.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mail merge in 2018 with R</title>
      <link>/2018/06/26/mail-merge/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/26/mail-merge/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Super cool 90s guy ready to surf the web (via Giphy)
 Two-thousand and late Clip art! Fax machines! CD-ROMs! Dial-up modems! The World Wide Web! Mail merge!
These exotic terms give me flashbacks to computer class at the turn of the millennium.
I have particularly fond memories of learning to mail merge, which was taught as a way to autocomplete template Word letters for made-up customers in some made-up Access database.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tid-ye-text with geniusr</title>
      <link>/2018/06/05/tid-ye-text/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/05/tid-ye-text/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
⚠️ Warning: this post contains offensive words. ⚠️
Genius? Kanye West released his latest album – ye – last week1 after a(nother) pretty turbulent and controversial period of his life2. So what’s been on his mind?
I think the real question is why don’t we scrape Yeezus’s lyrics from the web and analyse them using R? Obviously.
 Genius Genius is a website where you can upload and comment on song lyrics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloudy with a chance of pie</title>
      <link>/2018/05/25/cloud-pie/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/25/cloud-pie/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
The pinnacle of visualisation Great news everyone: I’ve taken the best of two stellar data visualisations and smashed them together into something that can only be described as perfection.
Let me set the scene. There’s three things we can agree on:
Everyone loves pie charts, particularly when they’re in 3D, exploded and tilted. Word clouds aren’t at all overused. I have too much time on my hands.  With that in mind, I’ve artfully melded clouds and pies into the function cloud_pie, which I think sounds rather sweet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TWO DOGS IN TOILET ELDERLY LADY INVOLVED</title>
      <link>/2018/04/27/two-dogs-in-toilet-elderly-lady-involved/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/27/two-dogs-in-toilet-elderly-lady-involved/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray (@mattdray)
Call the fire brigade. Oh wait, we’re fine.
 TL;DR Animals get stuck in weird places, just ask the London Fire Brigade. I used the sf package for handling some animal rescue spatial data prior to interactive mapping with leaflet. Scroll to the bottom to see the map.
 The problem Sometimes I work with eastings and northings coordinate data.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>