<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Rostrum</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Rostrum</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Pokeballs in Super Smash Bros</title>
      <link>/2018/05/19/pokeballs-in-super-smash-bros/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/19/pokeballs-in-super-smash-bros/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
Smash! Super Smash Bros (SSB) is a beat ’em up videogame series featuring characters from various Nintendo franchises and beyond.
The series has featured on Nintendo 64 (Super Smash Bros, 1998), Gamecube (SSB Melee, 2001), Wii (SSB Brawl, 2008), Wii U and 3DS (SSB ‘4’, 2014) and an upcoming title for the Switch console.
The game is popular enough to have resulted in a series of organised tournaments1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessibility workshop at #Sprint18</title>
      <link>/2018/05/12/accessibility-workshop-at-sprint18/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/12/accessibility-workshop-at-sprint18/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
Sprinting Sprint events are a chance for the government digital, data, design and technology community to:
 look back on the work we’ve been doing to transform government and to look forward at what we need to do
 Kevin Cunnington (@kevincunnington), Director General of the Government Digital Service (GDS), outlined this in a recent blog post.
This year’s major themes were transformation, innovation and collaboration. The event was held at the Southbank Centre and Royal Festival Hall in London, with 40 speakers, 19 workshops and over 700 delegates representing 40 departments and agencies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TWO DOGS IN TOILET ELDERLY LADY INVOLVED</title>
      <link>/2018/04/27/two-dogs-in-toilet-elderly-lady-involved/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/27/two-dogs-in-toilet-elderly-lady-involved/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
TL;DR Animals get stuck in weird places. Oh, and the sf package in R can be used for coordinate reprojection prior to interactive mapping with leaflet.
 The problem I often work with data that has coordinates; usually a eastings and northings. I need to convert these to latitude and longitude for interactive mapping using the leaflet package in R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Trek: exploring stardates</title>
      <link>/2018/04/14/r-trek-exploring-stardates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/14/r-trek-exploring-stardates/</guid>
      <description>Matt Dray
Captain’s log 📖  Star date 71750.51. Our mission is to use R statistical software to extract star dates mentioned in the captain’s log from the scripts of Star Trek: The Next Generation and observe their progression over the course of the show’s seven seasons. There appears to be some mismatch in the frequency of digits after the decimal point – could this indicate poor abillity to choose random numbers?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>